<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[David's Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[A starter blog demonstrating what Gatsby can do.]]></description><link>https://gatsby-starter-blog-demo.netlify.app</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 02:48:59 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[How Variable Ratio Reinforcement Hurts Novice Programmers]]></title><description><![CDATA[Variable ratio reinforcement schedules are powerful learning mechanisms that grip our minds. When applied nefariously, they can cause…]]></description><link>https://gatsby-starter-blog-demo.netlify.app/Variable-Ratio-Reinforcement/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://gatsby-starter-blog-demo.netlify.app/Variable-Ratio-Reinforcement/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 03:57:44 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simplypsychology.org/schedules-of-reinforcement.html#:~:text=A%20variable%20ratio%20schedule%20is,one%20needed%20to%20receive%20reinforcement&quot; title=&quot;Variable Ratio Reinforcement&quot;&gt;Variable ratio reinforcement schedules&lt;/a&gt; are powerful learning mechanisms that grip our minds. When applied nefariously, they can cause irreversible damage to even the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2016/12/losing-it-all/505814/&quot; title=&quot;Painful Story&quot;&gt;most smart, hardworking, and loving individuals.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And, If you’re not careful, they will also stop you from becoming a computer programmer.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Variable ratio reinforcement scheduling is just a psychologist’s way of describing slot machine style learning systems. Although most people understand slot machines have serious psychological risks, not all variable ratio reinforcement is bad. In fact, you probably happily use variable ratio reinforcement to successfully navigate your daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Super useful variable ratio reinforcement examples:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frequently thanking you partner for washing the dishes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasionally high fiving your toddler for sharing with a friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sorting your junk mail in hopes to find your Amazon package&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why am I arguing that variable ratio reinforcement can fundamentally prevent new programmers from learning the craft?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Because a novice programer often views the keyboard like a slot machine lever.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start out programming, you learn how to write very simple programs with very simple syntax. Your terminal may throw an error or two and you add a semicolon or a close parenthesis. Eventually you hit the right combo and are provided a fat reward! You printed out a fun (and probably profane) message to the screen and it feels damn good if you are even the least bit nerdy. A few more iterations through this stimulus/response cycle and you have been trained by variable ratio reinforcement to make some quick superficial changes to your code in order to get that sweet dopamine hit of a clean compile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time moves on, your learning exercises get a bit more complex. Maybe you forget there is a difference between &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;find()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;findIndex()&lt;/code&gt;, but it doesn’t matter because you’re happily programming. Your code is running but it’s not working as you intended. Although the best approach would be to pause and verify you understand what is happening at each line of code, you have been shaped to do something else!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You start changing some code around without thinking too hard and eventually change &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;find()&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;findIndex()&lt;/code&gt;. Maybe you remembered there was another function with that name, or maybe IntelliSense gave you the assist. Either way, your code works as intended again and you didn’t even have to look at documentation! Slot machine style debugging has extended its roots deeper into your limbic system all because of variable ratio reinforcement!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A novice programmer can effectively roleplay as a slot machine for a while. Even when faced with especially difficult problems, a novice programmer often will continue banging stuff together with a desperate hope of winning the jackpot. It’s not completely their fault. Behaviors trained by variable ratio reinforcement are &lt;a href=&quot;https://courses.lumenlearning.com/wmopen-psychology/chapter/reading-reinforcement-schedules/&quot; title=&quot;Reinforcement Schedule Comparison&quot;&gt;more resistant to extinction than those trained by any other reinforcement schedule.&lt;/a&gt; I am telling you, variable ratio reinforcement is strong stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So how does anyone learn best practices?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a novice programmer and are hoping to prevent the reward mechanisms of programming from damaging your early development, you have three paths to redemption!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Limit how often you engage in mindless code changes. If the reward from writing bug free code only comes after reading the documentation or making thoughtful code changes, variable ratio reinforcement will start to help you rather than hurt you! The same mechanism that locks your mind into bad habits will lock your mind into best practices!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Get &lt;em&gt;super stoked&lt;/em&gt; when your program works as intended. Get so stoked that you become willing to do anything for another hit of working code. Even if it means abandoning the slot machine paradigm in favor of best practices. If you go with this option, it’ll be a bit more painful than the previous option. You may bang your keyboard for a super long time trying to solve complex problems. But if you can get through the slot machine paradigm withdrawal symptoms, you’ll come out the other side!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path 3:&lt;/strong&gt; If you are so afflicted by the slot machine paradigm that the first two paths don’t work, there is still hope! You must now commit yourself to typing on your keyboard upside down while bug fixing. Do you think I’m kidding?! It will work! It’s so frustrating to type upside down that you’ll stop trying random changes and save the frustration only for quality attempts at fixing the code. If you’re concerned it’ll take too long to type upside down, dont worry. I promise it wont. Pulling on the lever forever while waiting for a payoff that never comes is what consumes too much time. And it may just kill your programming career before it starts.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>